<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Homelab on Caffeinspiration</title>
    <link>https://alexanderell.is/tags/homelab/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homelab on Caffeinspiration</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 20:48:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://alexanderell.is/tags/homelab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Checking if the Pi is done</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 20:48:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>I recently put together a Raspberry Pi cluster to try out some toy distributed systems projects, and I wanted to start with a basic monitoring program to get my feet wet and work out the following:
 Getting each node running and set up with software Running Go on each machine Deploying code to each machine Nodes listening &amp;amp; responding to RPCs Sending/receiving RPCs between laptop and nodes  As I&amp;rsquo;ve previously mentioned, this isn&amp;rsquo;t meant to be production grade, since I would just grab one off the shelf if that was the goal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Raspberry Pi Cluster for Building Toy Distributed Systems</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 20:48:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been getting more interested in distributed systems, and I wanted to get experience building some of the concepts I&amp;rsquo;ve read about.
My interest lies more on the software and system design side &amp;ndash; more &amp;ldquo;how would we design and build an example of a distributed file system across four computers?&amp;rdquo; than &amp;ldquo;how do I make a reliable home server to play media?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; which is why my focus is on playing around with some toy software problems instead of worrying about what a real production hardware setup would look like.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
