<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>design on Caffeinspiration</title>
    <link>https://alexanderell.is/tags/design/</link>
    <description>Recent content in design on Caffeinspiration</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 20:47:19 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://alexanderell.is/tags/design/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Clickbait Snail Mail</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/clickbait-snail-mail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 20:47:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/clickbait-snail-mail/</guid>
      <description>Junk mail is so interesting at its odd intersection between design, advertising, and psychology.
I usually try to pay attention to the ways that things around me are designed, and recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been saving some junk letters that are particularly interesting in their attention-grabbing efforts. Here are a few of the notable envelopes I&amp;rsquo;ve received in the past few months.
 What if we didn&amp;rsquo;t put any information on it and made it look exotic?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Design: Double Sided Park Signs</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/reservoir-signs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 23:52:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/reservoir-signs/</guid>
      <description>I often walk my dog around a small reservoir near my apartment. It&amp;rsquo;s a perfect distance for tiring a small terrier, and it&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful area.
There are a number of signs around the reservoir that tell you to not swim in the water (as it&amp;rsquo;s a backup emergency water supply) and to not walk on the ice when it&amp;rsquo;s frozen over in the winter (as it&amp;rsquo;s very, very cold if you fall in).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why does a spray bottle work?</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/check-valve/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 10:27:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/check-valve/</guid>
      <description>Exploring a simple machine I took apart a simple spray bottle to see how it kept fluid flowing only in one direction from the reservoir to the nozzle. It does so with simple check valves made of two pieces of plastic, a spring, and a small sphere. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple way to solve a tricky problem.
 A simple spray bottle  One way flow It&amp;rsquo;s often useful to restrict flow to only one direction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Letting the User Guide You: Analyzing Store Design</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/store-layout/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 09:02:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/store-layout/</guid>
      <description>I enjoy looking at design in everyday life and the balance between how things are designed and how people try to use them.
A store I visited recently had bad customer flow, and the signs were there. There was literally a sign telling customers where to line up for the checkout line. Customers didn&amp;rsquo;t naturally line up there, and an employee was correcting customers who missed the sign. This is bad design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MBTA Bus Mirrors</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/mbta-bus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 08:51:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/mbta-bus/</guid>
      <description>I take the MBTA 86 bus as part of my commute in the morning. It runs from Reservoir in Brighton to Sullivan Station in Cambridge, and it stops at Harvard on the way, which is where I get off.
Right after the Eliot street stop, there are two ways for the bus to get underground to the Harvard stop. One way is to go down Bennett St., take a right on University Road, take a right on Mt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noticing UI: Shazam&#39;s loading screen</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/noticing-ui-shazam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 21:29:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/noticing-ui-shazam/</guid>
      <description>Shazam&amp;rsquo;s loading screen I was pleasantly surprised by Shazam&amp;rsquo;s iPhone app loading screen, and I took a look into what makes it stand out.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what it looked like:
 This felt different, and it made me look at the experience of opening apps. I started by spending a bus ride home from work opening and closing apps to get a feel for why this wasn&amp;rsquo;t like other apps.
Loading&amp;hellip; A loading screen tells a user that the app or other result is not ready yet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
