<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Caffeinspiration</title>
    <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Caffeinspiration</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 11:37:37 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating a Bug in Moment.js</title>
      <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/investigating-moment-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 11:37:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/investigating-moment-bug/</guid>
      <description>Investigating a bug in Moment.js In this post, I walk through the steps I took while investigating a bug in Moment.js, an open source JavaScript library for dealing with dates and times. Rather than write about what would have ideally happened (the steps of which would look like 1) see bug, 2) know issue, 3) investigate fix, 4) open PR), I wanted to include the entire process, which included some</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting Arduino with a Node Server</title>
      <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/arduinode/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 09:59:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/arduinode/</guid>
      <description>Arduinode I&amp;rsquo;ve been working through the Arduino Starter Kit projects recently, and I wanted to try a new project that was outside of the pre-made booklet. Working with an offline Arduino (intranet of things?) has let me learn a great deal, and I wanted to see how difficult it would be to connect my Arduino to a simple Node server, which would get me ready to connect it in any future projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MBTA Bus Mirrors</title>
      <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/mbta-bus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 08:51:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/mbta-bus/</guid>
      <description>I take the MBTA 86 bus as part of my commute in the morning. It runs from Reservoir in Brighton to Sullivan Station in Cambridge, and it stops at Harvard on the way, which is where I get off.
Right after the Eliot street stop, there are two ways for the bus to get underground to the Harvard stop. One way is to go down Bennett St., take a right on University Road, take a right on Mt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Launching Breadth First Growth Newsletter</title>
      <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/shipping-breadth-first-growth/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Oct 2017 17:30:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/shipping-breadth-first-growth/</guid>
      <description>I recently started a weekly newsletter.
I love the idea of growing as a T-shaped developer. I had seen the term on Hacker News in reference to the Valve Handbook for New Employees:
 We value “T-shaped” people.
That is, people who are both generalists (highly skilled at a broad set of valuable things—the top of the T) and also experts (among the best in their field within a narrow discipline—the vertical leg of the T).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spaced Repetition Motivation</title>
      <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/spaced-repetition-motivation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 20:47:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/spaced-repetition-motivation/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been kicking around the idea of a spaced repetition app for a while now, and I&amp;rsquo;d like to explore some of the motivation behind this project.
With anything, the key to getting better is practice and repetition. The goal is deliberate practice and spaced repetition.
For me, one key to learning and getting better is making it easy to get to the uncomfortable state where I&amp;rsquo;m improving. This means very little analysis of what I should be studying and more time spent working.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Sensing with Arduino</title>
      <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/arduino-project-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 15:16:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/arduino-project-3/</guid>
      <description>I worked through the third basic project in the Arduino Starter Kit Projects Book. I like to write about the projects to reinforce my own understanding.
The third project, the &amp;ldquo;Love-O-Meter&amp;rdquo;, creates a simple circuit with a temperature sensor. Using the Analog-to-Digital converter, the Arduino reads in the value coming from the temperature sensor, then lights up a combination of 3 LEDs depending on that value.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what my circuit looked like:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noticing UI: Shazam&#39;s loading screen</title>
      <link>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/noticing-ui-shazam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 21:29:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderellis.github.io/blog/posts/noticing-ui-shazam/</guid>
      <description>Shazam&amp;rsquo;s loading screen I was pleasantly surprised by Shazam&amp;rsquo;s iPhone app loading screen, and I took a look into what makes it stand out.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what it looked like:
This felt different, and it made me look at the experience of opening apps. I started by spending a bus ride home from work opening and closing apps to get a feel for why this wasn&amp;rsquo;t like other apps.
Loading&amp;hellip; A loading screen tells a user that the app or other result is not ready yet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>