<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Caffeinspiration</title>
    <link>https://alexanderell.is/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Caffeinspiration</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 11:26:15 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://alexanderell.is/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>iPhones and action discoverability, or &#34;How the hell was I supposed to know that?&#34;</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/iphone-discoverability/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 11:26:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/iphone-discoverability/</guid>
      <description>Discoverability I spend a lot of my time thinking about UX and design, and I try to consciously think about it in the wild when I can. One of the things that always catches my eyes is the idea of discoverability, or how a user is able to discover that action X does some thing Y.
A basic way to do so is to rely on patterns that we&amp;rsquo;re all familiar with.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The hobby buyer&#39;s fallacy: &#34;I&#39;d really pursue my hobby if I just bought X&#34;</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/buyer-fallacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2022 10:13:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/buyer-fallacy/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s a trap I used to fall into that has happened more times than I&amp;rsquo;d like to admit1. The typical scenario would be something like this:
 There&amp;rsquo;s a hobby I&amp;rsquo;m into (or starting to get into) I find myself wanting to do that hobby more than I currently am I find some THING that seems like it would help I somehow convince myself that having that THING would make the difference I purchase that THING The THING only slightly helps, and I may or may not do the hobby more  Much like the scroll in Kung Fu Panda, the secret was really inside myself the whole time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stubbornness and programming</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/stubborn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2022 16:28:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/stubborn/</guid>
      <description>Every now and then, there will be the type of problem to solve where I know it will require an extra cup of coffee, a long block of dedicated time, and a lot of careful reading, debugging, note taking, and going for walks to think.
This is often &amp;ldquo;subtle bugs that are hard to repro but we need to fix&amp;rdquo; territory; it&amp;rsquo;s not fun greenfield development with a lot of brand new code (which, of course, would be a problem-free fresh start&amp;hellip;), but instead, probably a small PR with only a few lines changed that completely undersells the deep investigation required.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a toy WebSocket server from scratch</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/websockets-from-scratch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 12:06:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/websockets-from-scratch/</guid>
      <description>WebSocket (WS) connections are pretty neat. I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten to play around with them before, both for personal and professional projects, but my view has mostly been at a high level and concerned mainly with the things that I can build on top of them. I haven&amp;rsquo;t spent much time digging through the protocol.
I thought it would be pretty interesting to build a toy WS server from scratch. Like many other projects, I find building a toy system to be such a good way to learn more, and I&amp;rsquo;ll be talking about this toy WS server (and some of those things I learned) in the rest of the post.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What happens if you point two CNAMEs at each other? Not much, really</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/cnames/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Aug 2022 20:46:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/cnames/</guid>
      <description>I dabble with DNS for work, and I&amp;rsquo;m frequently checking if CNAMEs are properly configured. CNAMEs are Canonical NAMEs, kind of like nicknames, that indicate that one domain name is a nickname for another domain name. For example, you probably encounter CNAMEs that map from the classic www subdomain:
www.example.com CNAME example.com This entry indicates that example.com is the Canonical NAME for www.example.com. When you go to www.example.com, your DNS resolver sees this entry and looks up the right side instead, example.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sharpening the axe for programming</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/sharpening-the-axe/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Aug 2022 15:46:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/sharpening-the-axe/</guid>
      <description>A woodsman was once asked, “What would you do if you had just five minutes to chop down a tree?” He answered, “I would spend the first two and a half minutes sharpening my axe.”
 When it comes to solving a problem with code, I&amp;rsquo;ve found a few things that help make the process more efficient. The code is the output, but like sharpening the axe, there are a few things I do outside of writing code that makes it easier.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funny artifacts in a 3D house scan</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/3d-scan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jul 2022 13:16:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/3d-scan/</guid>
      <description>I like to window shop houses on Zillow. I really enjoy the recent trend of 3D interior scans, as they help give you a feeling for what the place is like, and it allows for another way to explore the space without seeing it in person, which is key for a good cross-country window shopping experience.
The other day, I was looking at a 4 story townhouse, and I noticed a few weird things on its 3D model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My false start when learning to program</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/learning-programming-false-start/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 16:35:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/learning-programming-false-start/</guid>
      <description>I got into programming after college, but there was a brief period of time when I had first tried to learn how to program. It didn&amp;rsquo;t stick, and I was thinking the other day about why that first attempt didn&amp;rsquo;t keep.
It was during one of my college summers (2012 or so) when I was working as an intern at a small law firm in Vermont. My day to day duties varied heavily, with some days being very busy and other days being filled with nothing to do, and in some of that downtime, I decided to learn to program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Work context, home context</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/context/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2022 12:38:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/context/</guid>
      <description>When I usually think about context in the meta, non-technical part of being a software engineer, I usually think of context switching and swapping your brain&amp;rsquo;s focus and working memory from one mode to another, switching from focused programming to a status meeting or trying to fit in a little coding time in the 30 minute blocks in between meetings.
Another aspect of context I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about recently is the separation of work context and home context.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to break the Envoy CI at head</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/break-envoy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2022 18:16:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/break-envoy/</guid>
      <description>I like to talk about small mistakes I&amp;rsquo;ve made. I&amp;rsquo;m a big proponent of psychological safety, and as a champion for it, I think it&amp;rsquo;s very important to talk about times you&amp;rsquo;ve slipped up or done something dumb. We all make mistakes, and there are times when you feel silly for doing something.
This is one of those times.
 I recently merged a large pull request in Envoy that required a lot of work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long running pull requests</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/my-longest-running-pr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jun 2022 11:45:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/my-longest-running-pr/</guid>
      <description>There&amp;rsquo;s nothing quite like merging a pull request that has been pending for months. It&amp;rsquo;s so satisfying.
At Google, they have little badges for your internal user profile. One of the ones you can get celebrates the longest time delta in between creating a change and submitting it. For example, if you create a PR on August 1st and submit it on September 1st, you&amp;rsquo;d probably get the 1-month PR badge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How far behind a plane is its noise?</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/plane-noise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jun 2022 10:03:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/plane-noise/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re ever near a relatively low flying airplane, you may have noticed that it sounds like it&amp;rsquo;s in a different spot in the sky than where it actually is. You can hear the loud engines, and your ears tell you it should be in one place, but your eyes tell you it&amp;rsquo;s clearly well ahead of its noise.
It&amp;rsquo;s a funny visual trick, and, living near the Boston airport flight path, I was thinking the other day about how it works.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I only care about the helpful notifications, not the promotional ones</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/sneaking-notifications/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jun 2022 10:54:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/sneaking-notifications/</guid>
      <description>Here&amp;rsquo;s a scenario. First, you download an app for a service that has some sort of in-person component, like picking up an order or meeting a driver at the curb. When using that app for the goal, be it that order or that meeting, it&amp;rsquo;s very helpful to have notifications, since they give you the current status and it can be important to coordinate.
You&amp;rsquo;d like to get a notification for when your order is ready, since that takes away the need for you to repeatedly poll the app and refresh constantly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing with a 3D representation of RGB color space</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/rgb-color-space/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 12:29:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/rgb-color-space/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m working on a color picking/finding game, and part of it will be asking the user to pick a color from a range of colors. This got me thinking: what are some ways we can represent RGB color space?
RGB One way to think of colors, especially colors on computers, is as a combination of three different primary colors: Red, Green, and Blue. If we say how much of each color we want, we can build a color from the values.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wikipedia Over WhatsApp</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/wikipedia-over-whatsapp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2022 17:37:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/wikipedia-over-whatsapp/</guid>
      <description>In-flight messaging I was on a Delta flight the other day, and I was thinking about how they offer free messaging from your smartphone.
How do they limit the wifi? Maybe they have some basic filter that says &amp;ldquo;deny everything except the urls for these 3 messaging apps&amp;rdquo;, which makes sense conceptually.
What if we don&amp;rsquo;t want to pay for wifi and we still want to be able to browse the web?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A basic ear training note matching game</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/note-matching/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 May 2022 01:03:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/note-matching/</guid>
      <description>This is a game for matching musical notes. JavaScript is needed to run this game. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have it enabled, I totally get it — I often don&amp;rsquo;t like it either. 
This is a simple ear-training game for matching notes. Play along with your favorite instrument!
You can also try singing/whistling, but note that the pitch detection is hand rolled and rough around the edges — apologies if it makes any mistakes, especially for lower notes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;I don&#39;t know the numbers&#34;: a math puzzle</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/numbers-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 15:29:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/numbers-game/</guid>
      <description>I saw a math puzzle the other day on Hacker News. It reads as follows:
 Two numbers are chosen randomly, both are positive integers smaller than 100. Sandy is told the sum of the numbers, while Peter is told the product of the numbers.
Then, this dialog occurs between Sandy and Peter:
Peter: I don&amp;rsquo;t know the numbers. Sandy: I don&amp;rsquo;t know the numbers. Peter: I don&amp;rsquo;t know the numbers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting comfortable with being uncomfortable</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/uncomfortable/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:28:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/uncomfortable/</guid>
      <description>Software engineering is cursed with uncertainty.
When we&amp;rsquo;re solving big new problems with software, if the exact problem has been solved before, we could just reuse the solution that already exists. Frequently though, the exact problem (or combination of problems) hasn&amp;rsquo;t been solved before, and we need to come up with a way to solve it.
Have you felt that feeling? That moment of uncertainty, where you don&amp;rsquo;t know what the solution will look like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opinionated variable names</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/opinionated-variable-names/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 13:08:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/opinionated-variable-names/</guid>
      <description>I think a lot about the human part of code, especially the work our brains do when writing and reading it and interfacing with the computer. Rachelbythebay had a great take on a way to inject some brain-processing into a technical task - when you&amp;rsquo;re running a command to affect n servers, maybe it would be good to type that number in manually.
 The idea is to force you to take in that number through your usual input devices (I&amp;rsquo;d say eyes, but some people are using text-to-speech stuff or similar, and they count too), chew on it with your wetware, and then feed it back into the computer somehow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a minute, really?</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/what-is-a-minute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2022 11:44:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/what-is-a-minute/</guid>
      <description>What&amp;rsquo;s in a minute? It can be sixty long seconds, or it can be just a blink of the eye.
Easy ways to slow time down If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to slow time down, see how long a minute feels for any of the following:
 If you&amp;rsquo;re able to, hold a plank for 60 seconds Read the Elementary Rules of Usage section from The Elements of Style If you&amp;rsquo;re able to, sprint at full speed for 60 seconds After asking a question to a group and hearing no response, wait for 60 seconds before offering the answer Try to hold your breath for 60 seconds  Easy ways to speed time up If you&amp;rsquo;re trying to speed time up, see how long a few minutes feels for any of the following:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The tech interview prep industry</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/tech-interview-prep-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 17:55:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/tech-interview-prep-industry/</guid>
      <description>Before I got into tech, I worked at a tutoring company in the Northern Virginia suburbs of Washington, D.C., doing a mix of schoolwork-related tutoring and standardized test prep.
From a business perspective, it made so much sense - you have kids taking standardized tests and parents who wanted their kids to do well on them. Here we have the SAT, a measurable evaluation that can be an immediate help to your future if you do well on it (though whether or not it&amp;rsquo;s truly a good evaluation is well beyond the scope of this essay).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keeping a debugging lab notebook</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/debugging-lab-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Mar 2022 13:09:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/debugging-lab-notebook/</guid>
      <description>I like to keep a debugging lab notebook when I&amp;rsquo;m working through a particularly tricky problem.
It&amp;rsquo;s nothing fancy, just a new tab visit to docs.new and a quick @today to add today&amp;rsquo;s date. I usually try to describe the problem and the specific issue I&amp;rsquo;m having, including any reproduction steps or screenshots (frequently copied over from the issue tracker). I try to summarize the issue and my understanding of how things work, though this frequently leads to a handful of open questions for me to go through to really understand what&amp;rsquo;s happening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detecting pitch with the Web Audio API and autocorrelation</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/tuner/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Mar 2022 13:00:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/tuner/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing with the Web Audio API recently, and I made a basic app that will detect the pitch of incoming tones using your microphone. You can try it by pressing &amp;ldquo;Start&amp;rdquo; (be sure to try both the sine wave and the frequency displays), and I&amp;rsquo;ll be walking through how it works below.
 Start
Press start to begin Rounding options:  No rounding Round to nearest Hz Round to nearest note  Smoothing options:  No smoothing Basic smoothing Very smoothed (note must be more consistent and held for longer)  Display (click Start after you switch):  Sine wave Frequency   Unfortunately, JavaScript is needed to run this.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I prefer my biographies in chronological order, thank you very much</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/chrono-bio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Mar 2022 18:52:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/chrono-bio/</guid>
      <description>Usually, biographies go through someone&amp;rsquo;s story in roughly chronological order.
OK, that&amp;rsquo;s a little too linear, like a page-a-day journal for your entire life. Realistically, you&amp;rsquo;re going to focus on different parts of the subject&amp;rsquo;s life more than others.
You can imagine that broken up into chapters, too. Maybe our subject&amp;rsquo;s childhood is generally passed over in favor of the more interesting middle-life.
This general flow makes sense, because you can do some fun foreshadowing by mentioning things that happen in the subject&amp;rsquo;s future (orange in the diagram below), and you can remind the reader of things that happened in the subject&amp;rsquo;s past with past references (purple in the diagram below).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My lizard brain is no match for infinite scroll</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/infinite-scroll/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2022 17:28:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/infinite-scroll/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m declaring defeat. Infinite scroll has won.
There is an endless supply of interesting things to consume online, and there are teams and teams of very smart people working very hard to get me to keep watching. One more video means one more metric counter incrementing, one more engagement click, one more step towards growth, ad revenue, product success&amp;hellip;
The danger for me is that I fall in. It&amp;rsquo;s so easy to open an app in an automatic movement of muscle memory, filling up an empty moment without conscious thought.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I miss easily seeing how my coworkers use tools</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/casual-collaboration/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 13:58:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/casual-collaboration/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s one of the little things I miss about working in-person with other people.
Writing software can involve so many different tools. Before my current remote working times, one of the ways I picked up on efficient ways to use some of the tools involved was from seeing how coworkers navigated them, especially when they had a lot more practice with them.
A colleague and I would be looking at their screen together, working with a tool that I had an OK understanding of, when they&amp;rsquo;d use a feature or shortcut I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Morse Codle</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/morse-codle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2022 21:03:02 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/morse-codle/</guid>
      <description>This is a game for playing Wordle with Morse Code. JavaScript is needed to run this game. If you don&#39;t have it enabled, I totally get it — I often don&#39;t like it either.     MORSE CODLE                                     q w e r t y u i o p   a s d f g h j k l   Enter z x c v b n m      --    Guess the MORSE CODLE in four tries.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing Morse code games in JavaScript using the Web Audio API</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/writing-morse-code-games/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 12:36:19 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/writing-morse-code-games/</guid>
      <description>Playing sound with the Web Audio API Playing Morse code  Morse code timing Playing letters, words, and sentences Adjusting the speed   The Listening Game     The &amp;ldquo;Speaking&amp;rdquo; game  Parsing the incoming signal into Morse code Hooking it up to user input   Finishing thoughts    Last week, I posted a pair of games I made to play with Morse code in your browser.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Little games to play with Morse Code in your browser</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/morse-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2022 22:32:54 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/morse-code/</guid>
      <description>Be sure to also check out my other Morse code game, Morse Codle, a daily Morse code Wordle puzzle.
This is a pair of games for playing with Morse Code. Since the games play the signals as sound, I recommend headphones (wired if possible for the latency) and a low volume. Game options are available towards the bottom.
 Unfortunately, JavaScript is needed to run these games. The only JS running on my site is for the games (no tracking, etc) if you want to enable it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a toy traceroute from scratch</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/toy-traceroute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jan 2022 10:59:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/toy-traceroute/</guid>
      <description>traceroute is a tool you can use to trace the route of packets from your computer to another computer. It lets you see each step that your packets take along the way.
For example, the following is the result of running traceroute from my computer in Massachusetts to &amp;ldquo;example.com&amp;rdquo;:
You can see that it took 8 hops to get from my computer to the destination IP (93.184.216.34), and you can see the associated timing for three different attempts for each step.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(1) New Message: How websites catch your attention with JavaScript</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/attention-javascript/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jan 2022 11:59:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/attention-javascript/</guid>
      <description>There are many good things about JavaScript. There are also bad things about JavaScript.
There are many cases of well-intentioned features in JavaScript being used for unhelpful purposes. These features can help support rich web applications with impressive features and capabilities, but they can often be used antagonistically, in the sense that they aren&amp;rsquo;t helpful for the user (like intercepting your clipboard commands). I find these cases interesting, and I wanted to explore a few of these attention-grabbing examples.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do you visualize code?</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/visualizing-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jan 2022 17:11:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/visualizing-code/</guid>
      <description>The other day I was reading about the development of personal computers and the desktop GUI, and I was thinking about how comfortable we all have become with the analogy of the &amp;ldquo;desktop&amp;rdquo; for our personal computers. We place files in folders and keep them on our desktops. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of physical action going on.
Humans are very good at understanding spaces, especially when it comes to remembering physical spaces, and it got me thinking about how we commonly visualize code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Children&#39;s Book Story About Distributed Systems</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/terrier-dist-sys/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jan 2022 20:07:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/terrier-dist-sys/</guid>
      <description>Editor&amp;rsquo;s note: the following document was found in a collection of papers and assignments, apparently dating from late 2020 when the author was stuck inside studying distributed systems. An additional note, written in green and red Crayon on the back of a CVS receipt, was found stapled to the document: &amp;ldquo;it is now winter . this work features only approximate explanations. it favors silliness over accuracy in some sections. it should be taken with a light hearted grain of salt&amp;rdquo; [sic].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Completing a Part-Time Master&#39;s in Computer Science While Working</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/mscs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jan 2022 17:33:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/mscs/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be 29 anyways, so I might as well be 29 with a Master&amp;rsquo;s.&amp;rdquo;
— me 5 years ago debating whether I should take classes
 On June 5, 2017, I started taking classes at Tufts University while working full time. On January 4, 2022, I submitted the final draft of my Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis. Much like my past self had hoped, I&amp;rsquo;ve made it 4 years in the future, and I&amp;rsquo;m done with my Master&amp;rsquo;s program.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Strange Path of Accepting How Your Brain Works</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/limitations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 00:10:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/limitations/</guid>
      <description>I recently read Turing&amp;rsquo;s Cathedral, a book about the early history of computers, and it largely focused on the life and brilliant times of John von Neumann, who was, to put it simply, a genius. It is both fascinating and disappointing to learn about a brain that works so much better than your own.
Fascinating because the wide spectrum of human ability has led to a brain so capable. That we (in the general, humanity sense of &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo;) are able to perform such feats is incredible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing an RPC From Scratch</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/rpc-from-scratch/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 13:15:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/rpc-from-scratch/</guid>
      <description>There are many ways for computers to talk to other computers. A commonly used approach is a Remote Procedure Call, or an RPC. An RPC allows for the abstraction of calling another computer&amp;rsquo;s procedure as if it were a local one with all of the transmission and communication taken care of.
Let&amp;rsquo;s say we&amp;rsquo;re writing some math program on a single computer and we have some procedure or function that handles checking if a number is prime.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>You&#39;re Reading This in the Future</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/youre-reading-this-in-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2021 19:39:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/youre-reading-this-in-the-future/</guid>
      <description>You&amp;rsquo;re reading this in the future. Isn&amp;rsquo;t that weird?
Even I&amp;rsquo;m reading this in the future. Let&amp;rsquo;s say I write the last &amp;ldquo;C&amp;rdquo; in this sentence at 7:41:50 EDT in the evening of Friday April 16, 2021, or exactly 1618616510 seconds since January 1, 1970, UTC. Even as I started typing this next sentence, let alone editing this and pushing this to my blog, that time has passed, and we&amp;rsquo;ve all moved on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Checking if the Pi is done</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 20:48:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>I recently put together a Raspberry Pi cluster to try out some toy distributed systems projects, and I wanted to start with a basic monitoring program to get my feet wet and work out the following:
 Getting each node running and set up with software Running Go on each machine Deploying code to each machine Nodes listening &amp;amp; responding to RPCs Sending/receiving RPCs between laptop and nodes  As I&amp;rsquo;ve previously mentioned, this isn&amp;rsquo;t meant to be production grade, since I would just grab one off the shelf if that was the goal.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Raspberry Pi Cluster for Building Toy Distributed Systems</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 20:48:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/pi-cluster/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been getting more interested in distributed systems, and I wanted to get experience building some of the concepts I&amp;rsquo;ve read about.
My interest lies more on the software and system design side &amp;ndash; more &amp;ldquo;how would we design and build an example of a distributed file system across four computers?&amp;rdquo; than &amp;ldquo;how do I make a reliable home server to play media?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; which is why my focus is on playing around with some toy software problems instead of worrying about what a real production hardware setup would look like.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debugging a launch-blocking issue</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/debugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Aug 2020 23:14:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/debugging/</guid>
      <description>It was around 4PM a few Fridays ago when I heard that something had gone wrong, and I volunteered (was volunteered?) to help fix it. There was a broken internal configuration that blocked future immediate work for an upcoming launch that same day. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t worked on this particular system, just similar things before, but because I&amp;rsquo;m decent at visualizing and debugging these things, my colleague asked me for help with it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Code Review and Criticism</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/me-and-my-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:07:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/me-and-my-work/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working in software for a few years, and I&amp;rsquo;ve come to take it for granted that I am not my work. My work exists in some separate sphere, where it can easily be critiqued, dissected, refactored, or improved by me or anyone else. It&amp;rsquo;s as if it&amp;rsquo;s in a separate pond from my private one, where any ripples don&amp;rsquo;t cross the pebbly barrier to the rest of me. I&amp;rsquo;m still proud of the things I make and still take ownership over code, projects, and problems, but those things are separate from me.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t touch my clipboard</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/taking-over-my-clipboard/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2020 18:01:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/taking-over-my-clipboard/</guid>
      <description>Looking for an em dash I was recently trying to find an em dash character to use in a piece of writing. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have the shortcut memorized—for future reference, shift+option+minus on Mac—I did a quick search for it. I didn&amp;rsquo;t see one on the search results page to copy, so I clicked into the first result: &amp;ldquo;The Punctuation Guide&amp;rdquo;:
From https://www.thepunctuationguide.com/em-dash.html
I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for a good copy and paste, so I selected the em dash character, copied it, and pasted back into my doc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harnessing the Power of Shower Thoughts</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/trust-in-your-unconscious/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2019 21:43:06 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/trust-in-your-unconscious/</guid>
      <description>One of the best ways to learn and come up with new ideas is to focus intensely on a problem, then let your mind wander. I&amp;rsquo;ve enjoyed doing this when problem solving and learning, and recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about how weird it is to build trust in your unconscious to do the work for you, especially when it comes to technical work.
Letting your mind focus and letting your mind wander The first recommendation I have for anyone taking a meta look at learning is Barbara Oakley&amp;rsquo;s Learning How To Learn.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dark pattern for autoplaying videos: clickjacking pause</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/intercept-pause/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 20:40:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/intercept-pause/</guid>
      <description>I recently saw a common clickjacking dark pattern when trying to pause a video the other day.
On a Bloomberg news autoplaying video, the sound is initially muted.
Clicking anywhere on the video will unmute it. It would be pretty easy to have an invisible element overlaying the video that listens for a click, and it looks like that&#39;s probably what we have here: What&#39;s interesting is that the control panel (pause, play, scrubbing, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clickbait Snail Mail</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/clickbait-snail-mail/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 20:47:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/clickbait-snail-mail/</guid>
      <description>Junk mail is so interesting at its odd intersection between design, advertising, and psychology.
I usually try to pay attention to the ways that things around me are designed, and recently I&amp;rsquo;ve been saving some junk letters that are particularly interesting in their attention-grabbing efforts. Here are a few of the notable envelopes I&amp;rsquo;ve received in the past few months.
 What if we didn&amp;rsquo;t put any information on it and made it look exotic?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MapReduce in Simple Language</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/simple-map-reduce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/simple-map-reduce/</guid>
      <description>MapReduce Explained Using the Ten Hundred Words People Use Most Often MapReduce is a good way to take a big job that would take a long time on one computer and break it up into smaller jobs that can be done by simple computers.
If you can break down a big job into smaller jobs, you can run the smaller jobs on many simple computers. If you have a lot of simple computers, you can do a lot of the smaller jobs at the same time, and this can make your job go a lot faster.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Good Design: Double Sided Park Signs</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/reservoir-signs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2018 23:52:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/reservoir-signs/</guid>
      <description>I often walk my dog around a small reservoir near my apartment. It&amp;rsquo;s a perfect distance for tiring a small terrier, and it&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful area.
There are a number of signs around the reservoir that tell you to not swim in the water (as it&amp;rsquo;s a backup emergency water supply) and to not walk on the ice when it&amp;rsquo;s frozen over in the winter (as it&amp;rsquo;s very, very cold if you fall in).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why does a spray bottle work?</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/check-valve/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 10:27:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/check-valve/</guid>
      <description>Exploring a simple machine I took apart a simple spray bottle to see how it kept fluid flowing only in one direction from the reservoir to the nozzle. It does so with simple check valves made of two pieces of plastic, a spring, and a small sphere. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple way to solve a tricky problem.
 A simple spray bottle  One way flow It&amp;rsquo;s often useful to restrict flow to only one direction.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Letting the User Guide You: Analyzing Store Design</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/store-layout/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 09:02:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/store-layout/</guid>
      <description>I enjoy looking at design in everyday life and the balance between how things are designed and how people try to use them.
A store I visited recently had bad customer flow, and the signs were there. There was literally a sign telling customers where to line up for the checkout line. Customers didn&amp;rsquo;t naturally line up there, and an employee was correcting customers who missed the sign. This is bad design.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a Simple Cache Server in Python</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/simple-cache-server-in-python/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2018 10:24:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/simple-cache-server-in-python/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a fan of small toy projects that have the sole purpose of demonstrating a concept. This is a small project that demonstrates how a cache server works.
I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to balance toy projects with getting exposure to production-level code. While this project has been helpful for understanding the idea, an open source project like [Squid-Cache] (https://github.com/squid-cache/squid) is definitely on my reading list!
At the very simplest level, an HTTP server responds to requests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating JavaScript&#39;s RegExp Lookbehind</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/regex-lookbehind/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 13:22:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/regex-lookbehind/</guid>
      <description>Some people, when confronted with a problem, think “I know, I&amp;rsquo;ll use regular expressions.” Now they have two problems.
 Jamie Zawinski
Regular Expression Lookbehinds I recently came across an interesting regular expressions use case that led to an interesting look into regular expressions, JavaScript engines, and release versions.
In particular, I was trying to find a certain substring from a string that did not contain a substring preceding it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JavaScript: Writing your own Array.reduce</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/javascript-array-reduce/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 09:51:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/javascript-array-reduce/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve found that one of the best ways for me to really understand anything is to implement it myself. Between the ECMAScript spec and a few lines of JavaScript, you can build a chunk of knowledge for a very specific area of JavaScript. Doing this often is a great way to gain a deeper understanding of the language, and it&amp;rsquo;s a great exercise in reading the docs, reading code, and creating your own solution.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>typeof null: investigating a classic JavaScript bug</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/typeof-null/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2018 08:40:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/typeof-null/</guid>
      <description>In my last post, I looked into some JavaScript casting and explored why 0 &amp;lt;= null evaluates as true.
For this post, I&amp;rsquo;d like to investigate another unexpected behavior in JavaScript: why typeof(null) evaluates as &#39;object&#39;.
This is a well-known bug, and we&amp;rsquo;ll investigate first in the ECMAScript specification followed by a deep dive into an early implementation of JavaScript to see the bug in its natural habitat.
The main idea is that the code assigned each item some bits for use as flags for different types, but null was different.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating JavaScript Casting Behavior</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/javascript-casting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2018 11:14:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/javascript-casting/</guid>
      <description>The disconnect between &amp;ldquo;what seems like it should happen&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;what happens&amp;rdquo; causes you to push doors that are to be pulled, tap ads that load in the place of content, and cast null into 0 by accident in JavaScript.
For more on JavaScript&amp;rsquo;s unintuitive behavior, please watch (or rewatch) wat.
Much of this behavior can be explained by JavaScript&amp;rsquo;s casting. From ECMAScipt: &amp;ldquo;The ECMAScript language implicitly performs automatic type conversion as needed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating a Bug in Moment.js</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/investigating-moment-bug/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 11:37:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/investigating-moment-bug/</guid>
      <description>Investigating a bug in Moment.js In this post, I walk through the steps I took while investigating a bug in Moment.js, an open source JavaScript library for dealing with dates and times. Rather than write about what would have ideally happened (the steps of which would look like 1) see bug, 2) know issue, 3) investigate fix, 4) open PR), I wanted to include the entire process, which included some</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Connecting Arduino with a Node Server</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/arduinode/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 09:59:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/arduinode/</guid>
      <description>Arduinode I&amp;rsquo;ve been working through the Arduino Starter Kit projects recently, and I wanted to try a new project that was outside of the pre-made booklet. Working with an offline Arduino (intranet of things?) has let me learn a great deal, and I wanted to see how difficult it would be to connect my Arduino to a simple Node server, which would get me ready to connect it in any future projects.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MBTA Bus Mirrors</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/mbta-bus/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 08:51:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/mbta-bus/</guid>
      <description>I take the MBTA 86 bus as part of my commute in the morning. It runs from Reservoir in Brighton to Sullivan Station in Cambridge, and it stops at Harvard on the way, which is where I get off.
Right after the Eliot street stop, there are two ways for the bus to get underground to the Harvard stop. One way is to go down Bennett St., take a right on University Road, take a right on Mt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Sensing with Arduino</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/arduino-project-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 15:16:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/arduino-project-3/</guid>
      <description>I worked through the third basic project in the Arduino Starter Kit Projects Book. I like to write about the projects to reinforce my own understanding.
The third project, the &amp;ldquo;Love-O-Meter&amp;rdquo;, creates a simple circuit with a temperature sensor. Using the Analog-to-Digital converter, the Arduino reads in the value coming from the temperature sensor, then lights up a combination of 3 LEDs depending on that value.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what my circuit looked like:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noticing UI: Shazam&#39;s loading screen</title>
      <link>https://alexanderell.is/posts/noticing-ui-shazam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Aug 2017 21:29:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alexanderell.is/posts/noticing-ui-shazam/</guid>
      <description>Shazam&amp;rsquo;s loading screen I was pleasantly surprised by Shazam&amp;rsquo;s iPhone app loading screen, and I took a look into what makes it stand out.
Here&amp;rsquo;s what it looked like:
 This felt different, and it made me look at the experience of opening apps. I started by spending a bus ride home from work opening and closing apps to get a feel for why this wasn&amp;rsquo;t like other apps.
Loading&amp;hellip; A loading screen tells a user that the app or other result is not ready yet.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
